[
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Catalytic hydrogenation of oils results in the production of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "soaps",
            "detergents",
            "alkanes",
            "butter",
            "margarine"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following reaction will not take place under normal conditions?<sub></sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Zn<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2HCI<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "Fe<sub>(s)</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4(aq)</sub>→ FeSO<sub>4(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "Cu<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2HCI<sub>(aq)</sub>→ CuCI<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "Ca<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2H Ca(OH)<sub>2(g)</sub>",
            "2Na<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(1)</sub>→ 2NaOH<sub>(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "A sample of orange juice is suspected to have been contaminated with a yellow dye. Which of the following methods can be used to detect the dye?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Decantation",
            "Chromatography",
            "Distillation",
            "Filtration",
            "Evaporation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "The electronic configuration 1s<sup>2 2</sup>2s<sup>2</sup>2p<sup>6</sup>3s<sup>2</sup>3p<sup>6</sup>is that of a",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "noble gas",
            "Group ll element",
            "Group lll element",
            "Group V element",
            "Group VI element"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "The heat accompanying the reaction represented by the equation H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>→ H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(g)</sub>is described as the heat of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "solution",
            "neutralization",
            "vaporization",
            "sublimation",
            "activation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Aluminum is above iron in the electrochemical series, yet iron corrodes easily on exposure to air while aluminium does not. This is because aluminium",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "has a lower density than iron",
            "is a better conductor than iron",
            "does not corrode spontaneously",
            "forms thin layer of inert oxide in moist air",
            "forms amphoteric oxides while iron does not"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "<p>When a solid melts and consequently boils, there is</p>",
        "explanation": "<p>- When a metal melts or boils, this is a change of physical state. Energy is transferred to a substance to melt or boil it.</p><p>- an increase in temperature will increase the average kinetic energy of the molecules.</p><p>- This energy is needed to overcome the forces of attraction between the metal ions and the delocalize electrons in the metal. The more energy needed, the higher the melting point or boiling point .</p><p> </p>",
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "a gradual increase in the average kinetic energy of the particles",
            "a sudden decrease in the kinetic energy of the particles",
            "no change in the average kinetic energy of the particles",
            "a rapid change in the nature of bonding of the components",
            "a change in the size of the fundamental particles"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following compounds will undergo additional reactions?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Ethyne",
            "Butane",
            "Pentane",
            "Tetrachloromethane",
            "Ethanol"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following reactions does not occur in the blast furnace during the extraction of iron?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub><sub>(s)</sub>+ 3CO<sub>(g)</sub>→ 2Fe<sub>(l)</sub>+ 3CO<sub>2</sub><sub>(g)</sub>",
            "C<sub>2</sub>+ CO<sub>2</sub><sub>(g)</sub>",
            "CaO<sub>(s)</sub>+ SiO<sub>2</sub><sub>(s)</sub>→ CaSiO<sub>3</sub><sub>(s)</sub>",
            "FeO<sub>(s)</sub>+ CO<sub>2</sub><sub>(g)</sub>+ Fe<sub>(l)</sub>",
            "2Fe<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(s)</sub>→ 4Fe<sub>(l)</sub>3O<sub>2</sub><sub>(g)</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "A catayst which increases the rate of a chemical reaction does so by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "increasing the reaction pathway",
            "increasing the surface area of the reactants",
            "increasing the pressure on the system",
            "decreasing the temperature at which the reaction occurs",
            "decreasing the activation energy of the reaction"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "How many molecules are there in 14g of nitrogen gas at s.t.p? (n = 14, Avogadro Number = 6. 0 x 10<sub>23</sub>mol<sub>-1</sub>)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "1.2 x 10<sup>23</sup>",
            "3.0 x 10<sup>23</sup>",
            "6.0 x10<sup>23</sup>",
            "1.2 x 10<sup>24</sup>",
            "30 x10<sup>23</sup>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following correctly explains entropy?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "the natural tendency for a system to achieve a greater disorder",
            "a balance of two driving forces between free energy and enthalpy changes",
            "the cause of spontaneity of a reaction",
            "a measure of the enthalpy of a reaction",
            "a measure of the rate of attaining equilibrum in a reversible reaction"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "<p>The gas that is liberated when iron is heated with concentrated tetraoxosulphate (VI)acid is</p>",
        "explanation": "<p>2Fe (s) + 6H2SO4 (l) → Fe2(SO4)3 (aq) + 3SO2 (g) + 6H2O (l)</p>",
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "H<sub>2</sub>S",
            "\\(SO_{2}\\)",
            "HCI",
            "SO<sub>3</sub>",
            "O<sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following salts in aqueous solution will have a pH greater than 7?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "NaCl",
            "ACI<sub>3</sub>",
            "FeCI<sub>3</sub>",
            "Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
            "K<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "The compound of copper which is used in electroplating dyeing, printing, wood preservation and as a fungicide is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "copper (ll) hydroxide",
            "copper (ll) trioxonitrate (V) pentahydrate",
            "copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (VI) pentahydrate",
            "copper (ll) oxide",
            "copper (ll) trioxocarbonate (lV)"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "What is the molecular formula of a compound whose empirical formula is CH<sub>2</sub>O and molar mass is 180? (H = 1, C = 12, O = 16)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub>O<sub>2</sub>",
            "C<sub>4</sub>H<sub>8</sub>O<sub>3</sub>",
            "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>10</sub>O<sub>5</sub>",
            "C<sub>6</sub>H<sub>12</sub>O<sub>6</sub>",
            "C<sub>12</sub>H<sub>22</sub>O<sub>11</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "MO and X<sub>2</sub>O represent the formula of oxides of elements M and X respectively . If M and X should combine to form a separate compound, what would be the formula of the compound?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "MX<sub>2</sub>",
            "M<sub>2</sub>X",
            "MX",
            "M<sub>3</sub>X<sub>2</sub>",
            "MX<sub>3</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following pollutants is biodegradable ?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Sewage",
            "Plastics",
            "Metal scrape",
            "Lead compounds",
            "Hydrogen sulphide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "In the reaction represented by the equation; 2FeCI<sub>3</sub>+ SO<sub>2</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>O → 2FeCL<sub>2</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>+ 2HCI the oxidation number of sulphur changes from",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "+2 to + 6",
            "+ 4 to + 6",
            "0 to + 6",
            "- 2 to + 4",
            "+2 to + 4"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following equations represents the reaction leading to the removal of permanent hardness of water?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Ca(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>→ CaCO<sub>3</sub>+ H<sub>2</sub>O + CO<sub>2</sub>",
            "MgSO<sub>4</sub>+ Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>+ Na<sub>2</sub>SO",
            "Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>+ 2HCI → CaCI<sub>2</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "Ca(HCO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>+ Ca(OH)<sub>3</sub>→ 2CaCO<sub>3</sub>+ 2H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "MgSO<sub>4</sub>+ BaCI<sub>2</sub>→ MgCI<sub>2</sub>+ BaSO<sub>4</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "The following alloys contain copper except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "magnalium",
            "duralumn",
            "bronze",
            "brass",
            "type metal"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "How many mole of AgNO<sub>3</sub>are there in 500cm<sup>3</sup>of 0.01MAgNO<sub>3</sub>solution?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "0.005 mole",
            "0.05 mole",
            "0.5 mole",
            "5 moles",
            "1 mole"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following statements explains why tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid is reqarded as a strong acid?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Tetraoxosulphate (IV) acid is dibasic",
            "the acid is concentrated",
            "the acid is complately ionized in aqueous solution",
            "tetraxosulphate (IV) ions are very reactive",
            "the acid is highly corrosive"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "<p>Which of the following is not correct of glucose and fructose?They</p>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "are structural isomers",
            "reduce fehling's solution",
            "can be obtained by the hydrolysis of starch",
            "are readily fermented by enzymes",
            "are soluble in water"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "To what temperature must a gas be raised from 273K in order to double both its volume and pressure?``",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "298k",
            "300k",
            "546k",
            "819k",
            "1092k"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following explains why trioxonitrate (V) acid is not used for preparing hydrogen from metals?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "it is volatile",
            "it is strongly oxidizing",
            "it forms a layer of oxide on the metal",
            "trioxonitrate (V) salts are soluble in water",
            "it renders the metals passive"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 27,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following is normally used for drying ammonia gas?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Concentrated tetraoxonitrate (Vl) acid",
            "Calcium oxide",
            "anhydrous calcium chloride",
            "phosphorus (V) oxide",
            "anhydrous copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (VI)"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 28,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Nuclear reactions can be used in the following except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "gauging the thickness of objects",
            "making atomic bombs",
            "curing cancer",
            "generating electricity",
            "purifying water"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 29,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "The decomposition of hydrogen peroxide is represented by the equation: 2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>+ O<sub>2</sub><sub>(g)</sub>what mass of hydrogen peroxide would be required to produce 22.4dm<sub>3</sub>of oxygen at s.t.p? (H = 1, O = 16, molar volume of a gas at s.t.p. = 22.4dm<sub>3</sub>)",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "18 g",
            "34 g",
            "36 g",
            "64 g",
            "68 g"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 30,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Which of the following compounds crystallizes without water of crystallization?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>",
            "CuSO<sub>4</sub>",
            "MgSO<sub>4</sub>",
            "NaCI",
            "FeSO<sub>4</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 31,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "The following metals are extracted by the electrolytic method except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "potassium",
            "calcium",
            "sodium",
            "tin",
            "magnesium"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 32,
        "year": 1990,
        "question": "Petrol can be obtained from diesel by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "distillation",
            "cracking",
            "catalysis",
            "polymerization",
            "dehydrogenation"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]